

Ph.D. Marco A. Lopez-Sanchez

Short bio: Marco is a postdoctoral researcher in the Dept. of Geology at University of Oviedo (Spain). He received his *Ph.D.* in Geology from the University of Oviedo in 2013 supervised by Sergio Llana-Fúnez. His thesis dealt with the study of a deep crustal-scale shear zone located in the hinterland of the Iberian massif. From 2013 till now, he combined jobs outside academia as Geology teacher and self-employed geology consultant with post-doctoral training in the Sergio Llana-Fúnez research group. So far, Marco has participated in four research projects.

His research interests range from different aspects of geodynamics, from microscopic to orogen-scale processes. Primary interests are rock deformation and rheology, crustal-scale shear zones, crustal strength modelling, characterization of rock microstructure using image analysis techniques, and understanding strain localization in nature. He also has academic interests in the geological mapping and evolution of ancient orogens, the interaction between rock deformation, fluids and metamorphism, and the establishment of the absolute time at which deformation processes occur. Marco also enjoys doing statistics, scientific computing, and programming to create scientific tools.

Personal details

Full name: Marco Antonio López Sánchez

Current (work) address:

Departamento de Geología Universidad de Oviedo Jesús Arias de Velasco s/n 33005 Oviedo Asturias, Spain

Tel: +34 985 103 120 (work)

e-mail: &&&@geol.uniovi.es (replace &&& with malopez)

On the web

web-page: http://bit.ly/geolUnioviMarco

CV (pdf): https://goo.gl/OnIYqH

Orcid-ID: http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0261-9267

Research-ID: A-4290-2015 Scopus author ID: 56320859100 Google scholar: scholargoogle Microsoft academic: 2116864491

Github page: https://github.com/marcoalopez

Education

Jul 2013 - Ph.D. in Geology, cum laude honours, Department of Geology, Univ. of Oviedo. Advisor: Sergio Llana-Fúnez. Co-advisors: Profs. A. Marcos and F. J. Martínez Thesis: Análisis tectónico de la Falla de Vivero (Galicia, NW of Spain)

Sep 2007 - DEA (Masters of Science - *M.Sc.*) in Geology, Department of Geology, University of Oviedo. Project advisor. Prof. A. Marcos

Jan 2006 - Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Geology, Department of Geology, University of Oviedo.

Research

Professional experience (only academic related)

Jun 2017 - present - Post-doctoral researcher, Dept. of Geology, University of Oviedo

Apr 2016 - Dec 2016 - Post-doctoral researcher, Dept. of Geology, University of Oviedo

Oct 2015 - Nov 2015 - Post-doctoral researcher, Dept. of Geology, University of Oviedo

2013 - 2015 - Research assistant (not-paid volunteer), Dept. of Geology, University of Oviedo

2007 - 2013 - Ph.D. candidate, Dept. of Geology, University of Oviedo

Fellowship/Awards

2017 - Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions Seal of Excellence Award with the research project proposal IDEA

2016 - Early Career Scientist's Travel Award for EGU General Assembly 2016

2007 - Doctoral fellowship (4 years) in the Severo Ochoa Program (FICYT, Principality of Asturias, Spain)

Publications

Published or in press (citable) peer-reviewed publications

Lopez-Sanchez MA and Llana-Fúnez S (2016) An extension of the Saltykov method to quantify 3D grain size distributions in mylonites *Journal of Structural Geology* **93**: 149-161; doi: 10.1016/j.jsg.2016.10.008

Lopez-Sanchez MA, Aleinikoff J, Marcos A, Martínez FJ, Llana-Fúnez S. (2016) An example of low Th/U zircon overgrowths of magmatic origin in a late orogenic variscan intrusive: the San Ciprián Massif (NW Spain). *Journal of the Geological Society* **173**: 282-291; doi: 10.1144/jgs2015-071

Lopez-Sanchez MA and Llana-Fúnez S (2015) An evaluation of different measures of dynamically recrystallized grain size for paleopiezometry or paleowattometry studies. *Solid Earth* **6**: 475-495, Special issue: Deformation mechanisms and ductile strain localization in the lithosphere; doi: 10.5194/se-6-475-2015

Lopez-Sanchez MA, Marcos A, Martínez FJ, Llana-Fúnez S, Iriondo A (2015) Setting new constrains on the age of crustal-scale normal fault (Vivero Fault): Implications for the evolution of Variscan orogeny in the Iberian Massif. *International Journal of Earth Sciences* **104**(4): 927-962; doi:10.1007/s00531-014-1119-1

Lopez-Sanchez MA, Iriondo A, Marcos A and Martínez FJ (2015) A U-Pb zircon age (479±5 Ma) from the uppermost layers of the Ollo de Sapo Fm near Viveiro (NW Spain): implications for the duration of rifting-related Cambro-Ordovician volcanism in Iberia. *Geological Magazine* **152**(2): 341-350; doi:10.1017/S0016756814000272

López-Sánchez MA (2007) Estudio geológico de la Falla de Vivero y estructuras asociadas en la región de Guntín (Lugo, NO de la Península Ibérica). *Trabajos de Geología* **27**: 97-157

Field Trip guides

Marcos A, Bastida F, Aller J, Fernández FJ, Llana-Fúnez S and **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (2011) DRT post-conference Fieldtrip Guide: West Asturian Leonese Zone, Cabo Ortegal, Malpica-Lamego Line. *Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT - Oviedo) meeting* 42 pp + map.

Meeting proceedings

- 2017 Llana-Fúnez S, Alonso JL, Caldera N and Lopez-Sanchez MA. Fault rocks at the base of the Somiedo Nappe (Variscan Orogen, NW Spain). Deformation mechanisms, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT) 2017 (Inverness, Scotland)
- 2017 Llana-Fúnez S, de Paola N, Pozzi G and Lopez-Sanchez MA. Slip events propagating along a
 ductile mid-crustal strike-slip shear zone (Malpica-Lamego line, Variscan Orogen, NW Iberia). European
 Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2016 Lopez-Sanchez MA and Llana-Fúnez S. Characterizing 3D grain size distributions from 2D sections in mylonites using a modified version of the Saltykov method (Oral). European Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2016 Lopez-Sanchez MA and Llana-Fúnez S. Caracterización de la distribución 3D de tamaños de grano en milonitas a partir de secciones usando el método Saltykov y una extensión del mismo (Oral). Congreso Geológico Nacional de España
- 2012 -Lopez-Sanchez MA, Llana-Fúnez S, Marcos A and Martínez FJ. Deformation of quartz and feldspar at mid-crustal depths in an extensional normal fault (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster).
 European Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2012 Lopez-Sanchez MA, Iriondo A, Marcos A and Martínez FJ. Una edad de 478,7 Ma (U-Pb Shrimp-RG) en la Formación Ollo de Sapo: implicaciones para el volcanismo Cambro-Ordovícico de la Península Ibérica (Poster). Congreso Geológico Nacional de España
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, LLana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos A. Strain gradient recorded in the Penedo Gordo granite during extensional movement of crustal-scale Vivero Fault (NW Spain) (Poster). European Geoscience Union General Assembly
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, LLana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos A. Changes in deformation mechanism and neocrystallisation in granite during a MT-LP deformation (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster). Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics meeting (Oviedo)
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, Llana-Fúnez S, Martínez FJ and Marcos A. Microstructural Evolution in Quartz and Feldspar During Medium T Deformation (Vivero Fault, NW Spain) (Poster). The Interrelationships Between Deformation and Metamorphism
- 2011 López-Sánchez MA, Marcos A, Martínez FJ and Llana-Fúnez S. Hangingwall Metamorphism Related to an Extensional Orogen-scale Shear Zone: The Vivero Fault (NW of Spain) (Poster). The

Interrelationships Between Deformation and Metamorphism

- 2010 López-Sánchez MA, Marcos A, Martínez FJ and Llana-Fúnez S. Microstructures from the footwall to the hangingwall in the Viveiro Shear Zone (NW of Iberian Peninsula) (Oral - by invitation).
 Sociedade Geológica de Portugal, VIII Congresso Nacional de Geología.
- 2009 López-Sánchez MA. Deformation partitioning patterns and metamorphism of the Viveiro shear zone (Guntín, NW of Iberian Peninsula) (Poster). Deformation, Rheology and Tectonics meeting (Liverpool)

Scripts developed and maintained

GrainSizeTools: A free and open-source Python script for estimating the grain size from thin sections Developed and maintained by: **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (stable) Info. & download: http://marcoalopez.github.io/GrainSizeTools/

Strength envelopes: A Python script to generate crust and lithoshere strenght envelopes Developed and maintained by: **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (currently under heavy development) Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/Strength_envelopes

JASPE: JASPE stands for *Just Another Stereoplot Python Environment*Developed and maintained by: **Lopez-Sanchez MA** (currently under heavy development)
Info. & download: https://qithub.com/marcoalopez/JASPE

Chemical age script: A free and open-source script to estimate the 'chemical' ages in monazites analyzed in electron microprobes

Developed and maintained by: Lopez-Sanchez MA

Info. & download: https://github.com/marcoalopez/chemical_age_script/

Training selected courses

2016 - Thematic School – Recrystallization Mechanism in Materials

Duration: 5 days (32 hours), Sète, France Coordinator: Maurine Montagnat

Organized by the CNRS "Groupement de Recherche" on Recrystallization (GDR3436). Certificate

2015 - Introduction to R Programming

Duration: 10 hours

Instructor: Filip Schouwenaars

Microsoft edx course (DAT204x). Certificate

2013 - Introduction to computer science and programming using Python

Duration: 210 hours

Prof. Eric Grimson, Prof. John Guttag, Dr. Chris Terman and Dr. Larry Rudolph Massachusetts Institute of Technology edx course (MITx - 6.00x). Certificate

2012 - Scanning Electron Microscopy and its applications to analyses of Rocks

Duration: 30 hours

Prof. John Wheeler, Dr. Elisabetta Mariani and Dr. Dan Tatham

Department of Earth, Ocean and Ecological Sciences, University of Liverpool

2008 - Training course in microtectonics

Duration: 30 hours

Institut für Geowissenschaften; Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz (Germany).

Analytical/technical skills

- Scientific computing and programming. Experience in Python programming language and several
 scientific libraries such as Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, and Pandas. I am also familiar with the basics of R
 programming language.
- Image analysis (ImageJ, Photoshop). Image enhancement, grain segmentation, shape descriptors, grain size, and spatial analysis.
- Scanning Electron Microscopy (BSD, EBSD); Familiar with the use of MTEX Matlab toolbox, HKL Channel 5 and the PFch5 script
- Grain size analysis. I use my own tools/scripts. See an example in http://marcoalopez.github.io/GrainSizeTools/
- **Electron Probe Micro-analyser **(EPMA). Including monazite chemical dating (see https://github.com/marcoalopez/chemical age script)
- Good theoretical background in understanding experimental data (i.e. statistics, interpolation and regression)
- Experience in geological mapping and Geographical Information Systems (GIS)
- U-Pb geochronological data treatment

Participation in Research Projects

2016 - present

Cataclasis y fracturación en rocas de la corteza continental (*Cataclasis and rock fracturing in the continental crust*). Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez Ref. MINECO-15-CGL2014-53388-P

2015

Procesos geológicos modeladores del relieve de la cordillera cantábrica. Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez Ref. FC-15-GRUPIN14-44

2010 - 2014

La transición frágil-dúctil de la corteza del NO penínsular (*The brittle-ductile transition in the continental crust in North-western Iberia*). Project led by Sergio Llana-Fúnez *Ref. MICINN-10-CGL2010-14890*

2007 - 2010

The tectonic evolution of an orogen in the transition between the internal and external zones: A comparison between the Variscan orogen in the NW of Iberian Peninsula and the Pyreneean Axial Zone (original title in spanish). Project led by Alberto Marcos. Ref. CGL2006-08822/BTE

Teaching (at university level)

Accredited as an assistant teacher by the National Agency for Quality Assessment and Accreditation of Spain (ANECA) in 2016

Graduate teaching assistant from 2009 to 2011 and in 2017 at University of Oviedo

Laboratory sections taught: Plate Tectonics (20 hours); Structural Geology (20 hours); Geophysical and Geochemical prospecting (10 hours); Interpretation of geological maps (10 hours)

Field Camp taught: Geodynamics (10 hours); Structural Geology (10 hours); Fieldwork (geological mapping)

Administrative experience

Deformation mechanisms, Rheology and Tectonics (DRT2011) meeting organizing committee. DRT meetings are a series of biannual international meetings dedicated to the study of deformation processes in rocks at different scales, from the microscale to the study of bulk deformation of the lithosphere

Languages

Spanish (and Galician) mother tongue English (fluent); Portuguese (reading fluently and listening comprehension)

Last update: 2017/10/08

Copyright © 2017; Road on header image by Kamil Lehmann on Unsplash (CCO)

Hosted on GitHub Pages — This website was created with Typora